<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Off-topic | License to Kill -9]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.flaviocaetano.com/blog/categories/off-topic/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.flaviocaetano.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-29T15:13:44-02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.flaviocaetano.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Flávio Caetano]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[flavio@vieiracaetano.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cicada 3301 Lives!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.flaviocaetano.com/post/cicada-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-06T14:19:11-02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.flaviocaetano.com/post/cicada-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This morning, Cicada 3301 went back to active! In his/hers <a href="https://twitter.com/1231507051321">Twitter account</a>
used on last year’s challenge there was new link to an image posted on imgur.</p>

<p><a href="/images/zN4h51m.jpg"><img src="/images/zN4h51m.jpg" alt="First Chapter" /></a></p>

<p>Reproducing the tradicional previous steps, by extracting the image using
<a href="http://www.outguess.org/">outguess</a> we came onto a message, once again signed.
Its authenticity could be proved using Cicada’s previous known
<a href="http://pgp.mit.edu:11371/pks/lookup?op=vindex&amp;search=0x181F01E57A35090F">public key</a>.</p>

<p>Now let’s get our hands dirty! The first task was easy, since it’s steps were
already elucidated on previous years. Now things start to get interesting.</p>

<p>If you’re interested in following the challenge progress, <a href="http://uncovering-cicada.wikia.com/wiki/CICADA_3301_2014_PUZZLE">Uncovering Cicada</a>
is on a good pace.</p>

<p>Good luck, and good hunting!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Tale of Luck]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.flaviocaetano.com/post/the-tale-of-luck/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-27T18:40:44-02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.flaviocaetano.com/post/the-tale-of-luck</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“Once upon a time, there was a tiny invisible force named <em>Luck</em>. Everybody loved
it and gave it gifts, hoping that, when needed, <em>Luck</em> would come for them. But
<em>Luck</em> had a younger sibling called <em>Bad Luck</em>, who hated <em>Luck</em> with all it’s
strength and always tried to be the opposite of <em>Luck</em>, because, while everybody
smiled and cheered for <em>Luck</em>, no one liked when <em>Bad Luck</em> was around. People
twisted their noses at <em>Bad Luck</em> and everybody blamed it for every bad thing that
happened in their lives.”</p>

<p>This is that time of year when joy and happiness take over people. Some folks are
going on vacations and we won’t see again for a while, and every single one of
them, without exception, while saying goodbye, wish “happy holidays, and good
luck!” If there’s one thing I can’t understand is this misconception people have
on <em>luck</em> and <em>bad luck</em>. I see all those people on new year’s eve wearing white,
jumping waves, and doing all kinds of foolishness hoping it “will bring them good
luck” and I can’t understand.</p>

<p>Luck isn’t something you can “force” or hope to come. “Luck” is the name we give
for a chain of events that, coincidentally, affect you in a good (<em>luckily</em>) or
bad (<em>unluckily</em>) way. Let’s picture an hypothetical scenario: you’re riding a
bike and, right before you cross another street, you hit a pedestrian. Was bad
luck that put that asshole there, right? Now, what if, one second after you hit
him, a car goes by at 60mph crossing the street you are at. Not so bad luck hitting
that good citizen now, huh? So, although the result is the same, the denomination
we give to that chain of events changed because of one single variable: some
douchebag driving his car while talking on the phone. So, what was bad luck for
you, became luck. But what about for that poor guy you hit? For him, independently
of the result, he’s still pretty banged up, so he <em>had</em> bad luck. It didn’t
randomly pointed at him and said “you, sir, are gonna get screwed!” It did just
happened. Bad Luck. When you do something that goes badly and you knew the odds
were against you, that’s not bad luck. It’s not the universe flipping you the
finger and screaming “fuck you, Jimmywobble!” That’s stupidity. <em>YOLO</em> my ass!</p>

<p>I not always wear white on new year’s eve, but when I do, it’s not because I think
it will bring me peace in the upcoming year. It’s because I want to get into the
spirit of the party. Those thousands of people in white, happy, drunk and with
the promise of better things to come are what drive me to join them and put on a
white shirt.</p>

<p>But don’t think I’m crazy just yet. If I’m walking down the street and I see a
ladder landing on a wall, of course I’ll pass around it. Not only I do not want
anything to fall on my head, but hey, what if I’m wrong? Why would I bet against
it when I don’t know if it will get angry and come back to bite me in the ass?</p>

<p>So, in this year’s ending, I wish that every single little incident that happens
to you in 2013 may be chained to good fortune. I hope that slam you’ll give with
your pinky finger in your table helps you find that earring you’re looking for
for three years. Or that tongue bite you’ll have may lead you into meeting some
super hot nurse.</p>

<p>So I wish you well in the new year. I hope you all the best.</p>

<p>And good luck.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Once Upon a Time, There Was Nothing]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.flaviocaetano.com/post/once-upon/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-21T13:55:49-02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.flaviocaetano.com/post/once-upon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi there, stranger.</p>

<p>If you found this blog, you’re probably my friend or already know what I do for
a living. But anyways I’m a mobile app developer (I mean, iOS developer), Python
fan and Django explorer.</p>

<p>In this blog, which I’ll try to update at least once a month, I’ll primarily talk
about my approaches in some aspects of my developer life, but if I digress and
start talking about karting, movies, cooking or anything, please, bare with me 
for I’ll eventually come back to topic – or not. Those are some of my current
hobbies and, in the future, more wil come and some will be forgotten.</p>

<p>That’s me. Oh, btw, my name is Flávio (duh!), I’m 22 brazilian and you can reach
me at <a href="mailto:flavio@vieiracaetano.com">flavio@vieiracaetano.com</a>.</p>

<p>These are some of my links you may find interesting:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/fjcaetano">Github Profile</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://flaviocaetano.com">Personal Page</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/flavio-vieira-caetano-8267851a/">LinkedIn Profile</a></li>
</ul>

<p>That’s it for now. Soon will finish the next article I’m currently working on
and, when I’m satisfied – which will probably be never, but I’ll post it anyway
– we’ll talk more.</p>

<p>See you next time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
